Hey guys, welcome to the second session
on how to grow a small trading account
of around $10,000.
So, in last week's session we went over
you know, foundation and mindset, you
know, why most small accounts fail by
over-leveraging, the power of
journaling, we went through that in
depth.
Uh, the math of survival, asymmetric
loss versus gain, position sizing, and
risk management. And why going big is a
sure fire way to failure.
Today, because obviously, um, I have
limited time each day to cover these
topics.
But today we're going to delve into
session two, which is strategies, right?
Obviously, naturally the the next
progression is
"How do I actually grow my account and
what strategies are good to be using,
right?"
Um, so in this we'll cover why strategy
choice is constrained by account size,
uh, margin requirements versus buying
power, uh, avoiding naked options to
find risk being paramount, obviously,
four strategies, and then underlying
selection. So,
the first thing is is that with a
smaller account, you're you're not able
to do all the strategies that
a more well-capitalized account is able
to do.
And that's just a function of of of not
having enough margin in your margin
account to actually, you know, uh, open
positions that larger account is able to
open, for example. Um,
having buying power to buy a higher
priced name, let's say a Tesla like $405
a share, or an Amazon at, you know, 248
roughly,
um, or a Micron which is trading over
$1,000 per share,
you're obviously very limited, right?
You can't just can't just go out and buy
100 shares of that asset if you're
trying to trade options on it. Uh, and
so you're kind of focused on strategies
that allow you to grow your account in a
responsible way, but from a small,
>> [clears throat]
>> uh, number and small risk overall.
And so, these strategies really are all
all around, um,
you know, well, to start off, long puts
and long calls, right? You buy a put
option, you buy a call option, you have
unlimited upside on the call option, you
have,
um, theoretically, well, not really
unlimited upside on the on the put
option because the maximum you can make
is from your strike price to zero, but
if you look at an option chain, and
let's look at, for example,
uh, Nvidia over here because we used
that other example last week. I mean,
I'm going to use Nvidia because it's
it's a it's a name everyone understands,
knows for the most part, and we're all
familiar with it. I want to be
consistent across this, um, these
modules, anyway.
So, right now you have an asset that's
$210,
approximately, USD per share.
And to buy 100 shares would cost you,
uh, about $21,000 US, right? The reason
why I mentioned 100 shares is because
each option contract that you buy
gives you the right to buy or sell 100
shares of that asset.
So, if you're buying, you know, for
example, the 200 strike call option that
expires in July, which is about a month
away, on Nvidia,
and you say, "You know what? I could buy
100 shares if I had $21,000 in my
account." Again, we're presuming here
that you have maybe 10K in your account.
Well, instead, you're you're far more
limited, right? You could buy, instead,
a position that acts almost as a as a
proxy for owning Nvidia in that you buy
a call option at the $200 strike price,
that would be in the money,
and you'd be paying about $15 for that
contract, which means you're paying
$1,500 because each contract covers 100
shares.
And [clears throat]
not diving into like the the nuances of
the Greeks here because that's not the
point of this discussion, but
essentially here, you're paying a
premium of about $5 over the current
price.
That's the cost of doing business by
having this leverage in your portfolio
because as a 10K account, you cannot
afford to buy 100 shares, but you can
buy one call option.
And so with this in mind,
let's say you have a thesis for example
that Nvidia is going to run to, you
know, 230 by the expiration date July
17th. Well,
if you were correct
on that assumption, you would
essentially double your money on this
position. So you turn $1,500 roughly
into $3,000 and on a 10K account, that
would require you to risk 15% of your
account to make a return of 15%.
Now, on that note,
let's say you're bearish instead on
Nvidia obviously, right? You could buy a
put option
and you could buy one in the money as a
proxy for being short the stock.
Again, a similar idea would be buy the
220 strike call uh put option, $50
roughly, and let's say you thought it
was going to 190 for example by July
17th,
then you would make $15 profit on this
put option. But notice how on both these
contracts, there is a premium attached
that you're paying a $5 premium above
the current price. That is the risk
premium on these options, right? Because
naturally if options traded at a pure
intrinsic value where there was no
detriment to you owning the option
versus the stock, there would be no
impetus for anyone to actually own the
stock. Everyone would just own the
options because they're a fraction of
the cost and they're far more capital
efficient.
Um
the way you can kind of think about this
is a little bit is like, you know,
getting a mortgage on a house versus
buying in cash outright. Buying an
option is similar to buying a mortgage.
Um the only difference being that you
have no collateral behind buying that
option, right? If you want to actually
own the asset at the expiration date,
you need to have enough capital to take
assignment of that asset. And given that
Nvidia is, you know, 210 a share
roughly, you need $21,000 in capital or
equivalent margin in your port you know,
in your account in order to actually
take assignment of,
for [clears throat] example, a $200 call
option if it expires in the money.
So,
um you have these, you know, basic
strategies, buying a call, buying a put.
And you might think, okay, well, I could
buy an out of the money call or out of
the money put as well.
And that is a reasonable assumption
because obviously the asymmetry of risk
is pretty incredible. You can go out of
the money further and further, and the
the further you go out of the money, the
cheaper the option gets. But the
trade-off is that the
probability of that option expiring with
some value is not very high. You require
a much, much larger move to occur in
your favor very quickly in order to make
money on that position.
This is why
brings us to our next kind of discussion
point, right? Because I don't think
buying single legs, calls or puts is the
most constructive way to grow a small
portfolio. You you have to take too much
risk uh on a percentage basis to make
perhaps great reward, but at the same
time you want to be consistent here,
right? The The focus is on being
consistent, not on hitting the one-off
home run where you might double your
account value very quickly, but
alternatively, you might lose half of
your account.
So,
if we go from just, you know, a long
call or a long put,
we focus now instead on vertical
spreads, debit and credit spreads. These
are the best options cuz they're they're
defined risk and they require far lower
capital.
So,
going back to our discussion on Nvidia,
um
it's like my screen is a bit frozen.
There we go.
On the same line of thinking that we had
before,
instead of just buying the call option,
we can in our margin accounts sell a
call option against our call option, or
we can sell a put option against our put
option, right? Creating a call spread or
a put spread.
Um
Now,
let's say for example that the first
step that I always take myself, just for
you guys to know, is I look at the the
straddle price. Cuz that gives me an
inclination as to what the market
expects the underlying asset to do by a
certain uh expiration date. So,
the current closest strike price to the
current spot price is 210.
And the straddle right now is pricing
in, if you combine these costs, you have
210 call and a 210 put.
And the combined cost here is about
$17.20.
That tells us that the market expects
Nvidia to move up or down
from this current price, 210 roughly,
uh uh by about $17 by July 17th.
So, now we can kind of like we go to a
chart and say, "Okay, well, given that
we know that the market's pricing in
this kind of range,
how do we want to express our overall um
positioning there?"
All right, guys, one sec, guys. When I
have Zoom running and IBKR with all the
charts and stuff, it just it bogged my
system down.
Doesn't matter how much RAM you have.
It's like I uh IBKR is a huge RAM hog.
So,
here we go. One sec, guys.
So, looking at the chart, we can
establish
essentially the range um on the chart
ourselves.
So, we draw two lines,
$17 above and below the current price.
So, 210 minus 17 is like is 193,
somewhere around here.
You notice I have this alert set our
morning meeting which we discussed um
a trigger uh point to like go long here
and and buy some or
buy some calls or perhaps stock here
perhaps uh if it goes up well again. And
then the other point would be 210 plus
17 which is 227.
So near the highs over here.
So so now now you have this kind of
range established, right? You can go up
or down from the current price.
You can go up to here
or we could also go down to
here.
That's the range we're looking at for
the month ahead. So
this is this is a good way to think
about
>> that?
>> This is a good way to think about uh
Sorry me sorry guys uh John's mic was
was open there. Um this is a good way to
think about how to structure your trade,
right? Unfortunately right now we're
kind of in the middle of this of a of
like a of a range here.
It looks like we're we're going to break
back up toward the highs again, but
we're not at a really great point to
give you um a high confidence trade. But
the the point of this of of of this
discussion is not to elicit like uh you
know, a high confidence trade overall
perhaps, right? It's just discuss
strategies that you could use, right?
So let's presume that maybe you're
bullish uh into the July op ex instead
of being bearish, right? Well, naturally
you want to look at that 230 roughly
area as a target based upon the current
straddle price.
So again, going back to our chart to our
option chain now.
We look at
That's slow.
One sec, guys.
There we go.
Um we look at a target of
230 approximately, right? So there are
many ways you can express this overall
thesis. You could go, you know, in the
money call spreads, you could go with
with an at the money call spread
perhaps.
Uh you can go with an out-of-the-money
call spread. It really depends on what
your overall focus is. Do you want
higher probability, lower profit trades?
Or do you want lower probability, higher
profit trades?
Said differently, do you want to have
more units of
reward per unit of risk? Or do you want
to have, you know, lower amounts of
reward with higher probability
essentially, right?
So, here you can look at, for example,
let's say we said, "Okay, I think it's
going to go to 230 by expiration." I can
buy this call option, 210 strike price,
and sell the 230 strike price call
option against it. Now, my cost basis
goes down to about $6. Now, I'm risking
six and change to make a maximum profit
of 230 to 210 is 20, minus six is 14.
I'm risking six to make 14.
And this is kind of the way you got to
think about your your trade structure.
Using spreads will be your friend,
because even though you're going to cap
your gains, the intention is not to hit
on
home runs, it's to hit base hits
recurringly with decent degrees of
profit where your risk is capped.
So, in this scenario, you're risking
about on a 10K account 6% of your
portfolio to make an additional return
of 14% on your portfolio.
You might perhaps have a
mental stop loss of like 50% of the
position, which is what I typically do
is I say, "Okay, if it hits, for
example, half the value of my entry
point, $3 in this case, perhaps, you
stop out, take a loss, admit that you
were incorrect, perhaps, and then move
on to the next trade, right?" A very um
like automatic approach, robotic
approach, some may say, but it's the way
that you want to kind of develop your
pattern of decision-making with respect
to finding um consistency in your
in your in in your overall outcomes
overall, right?
So, you can go, you know, 20 wide
perhaps, or make or maybe you say to
yourself, you know what, I'm not
comfortable with taking 6% risk. I want
a bit less risk, right? Well, if you go
out of the money instead,
let's say you roll up to the 220 strike
instead,
230 call spread, so 220 230 call spread,
long this, short this. Now, you're
risking $200 and change
to make a maximum profit of about $800.
You're risking 2% of your portfolio to
make a maximum profit of 8%, right? So,
you're capping your gains, but your risk
is much much lower. And if you got again
use the same rule that I use, which is
to cut half or sorry, cut my position if
and when it hits 50% maximum loss, if
I'm sizing um my my typical size, then
you're going to cut it out of the loss
of roughly $100 or so.
You're pretty much pretty much saying
mentally, I'm okay with losing $100 or
1% of my portfolio, because I have
upside here of, you know, 8% roughly.
And you might not even target the
maximum 8% because if for example Nvidia
shoots to like 225 tomorrow,
would you be willing to hold that trade
for the next 30 days where you're
risking $5 to make five more dollars?
The answer is probably not,
unless you've in some way de-risked your
position where let's say for example you
have two contracts or two spreads, and
they go from $2 and change to $5, in
that case you sell one of them, now you
have a free position, right? It it
removes the emotion from the
decision-making process, which is what
you want to do essentially. The
again, I'll say it again and again,
the best way to think about trading is
not about optimizing or maximizing the
profitability, it's about minimizing
your emotional attachment to each
decision you make. Because ultimately,
emotions are what elicit bad
decision-making making processes over
over time overall, right? Like think
about a time when you guys have had
perhaps a terrible outcome, what has
precipitated that that terrible outcome?
I would wager that
you've probably taken some stupid amount
of risk on a lower probability trade.
Maybe you've averaged in an additive to
a losing position recurringly. You sized
way long way larger than you thought you
would. I had a student a few years ago
during COVID and he made a lot of money
during that rally up like 2020 to 2022
roughly. He made about $5 million
roughly.
And in
2023 when we had that little bit of a or
that that bear market in tech, namely,
he started off with one position in the
Nasdaq. Long tech. And as it started
falling, he started adding to it. And
before he knew it, he ended up losing
700k and it snowballed into him making
bad worse and worse decisions overall.
Long story short, he ended up losing
$3.6 million or so
of his $5 million and change of profit
that he had earned in the prior couple
of years. So imagine how terrible he
felt, right? But again, that's where it
doesn't matter how good of a trader you
are, it only takes one stupid decision
or one mistake to erase your entire
career's worth of good decisions
perhaps, right? Like imagine for example
Warren Buffett said, "Hey,
I'm going to go and YOLO before I
retire. I'm going to take everything I
have. I'm going to buy out of the money
SPX put options on some kind of hunch or
whatever. They expire worthless. It
doesn't matter that he made all that
money over his whole career and was very
very astute and wise and and disciplined
in doing it. That one decision that he
made just obliterated every past
decision he ever made. So again, the
same can be said for anyone, right?
Which is also why I I I put little
credence into anyone that shows me like
one good trade because ultimately it's
it's what it's what you do day in day
out that will elicit consistency in your
outcomes, right?
Um I'm not really impressed by anyone
that hits a home run on on some gamble
because ultimately
it's not a repeatable process, right?
What you want to do is find a repeatable
process and using verticals or spreads
um is a great way to do that, right?
Again, you can use call spreads, you can
use put spreads. It's kind of
it it doesn't really matter. It depends
on your overall thesis, right?
So,
um
let's say you're bullish here again,
you're risking two to make eight. You
could you could also roll down and have
different outlays. Let's say you want to
go for example
uh higher probability with lower profit,
you might go 210 to 220 for example.
In this case, you're now risking four to
make six. You can see where I'm going
with this, right? As you go in the money
further and further, the asymmetry of
risk worsens, but the probability of
making that profit increases overall,
right? So, you got to kind of find a
happy medium there where you're being
realistic about your your your outcome
expectation and not being too outlandish
and saying, "Hey, you know what? I'm
going to buy the cheapest call option
because I can buy a 250 strike call
option for 70 cents for example, right?"
And a lot of people would do that and
say, "Well, they're cheap, so why not
buy that?" Well, I would say the
probability of that hitting based on the
current delta right now is about 7%.
Therefore, I would maybe sell that
contract and say, "You know what? I'm
not enthusiastic about buying that
contract."
So, again, same amount of thinking can
be applied to buying a put a put spread.
Let's say you're bearish, you might say,
"Okay, well, you know what? I think
we're going to go to 190. I'm going to
go long the 200 strike price and short
the 190 here overall, right? Again,
similar outlay, risking two roughly to
make eight. Exact same thought process
just in reverse, I'm bearish instead of
being bullish, right?
Now, taking this one step further where
when you understand the nuances of
option trading, uh which not everyone
does. Most people don't actually and
I've I've worked with many many people
that
think they know about options because
they traded them perhaps for, you know,
a few years, but they don't understand
the nuances behind them. And that's
where you get the the true edge in
understanding how to strategize and
manage your risk by understanding the
different variables that play into how
an option moves.
So, we go from vertical spreads
to now butterfly spreads, right? They're
a compromise on taking a directional
bias and a very powerful strategy
because you're a net seller of options
in this instance. And for those of you
guys that don't know what a butterfly
is, it's where you buy a call option or
a put option. I'll I'll demonstrate an
example here.
So,
back to Nvidia again just to keep
consistent here, right? So, let's let's
say we have this the same thesis. It's
going to
Nvidia's going to go to 230 a share by
July 17th, right? Well, I could for
example, you know, buy a call spread or
I could buy a call option. There are
many different ways like there are an
infinite number of permutations you
could take to express your idea here,
right? But, let's say that I wanted to
be structured and methodical with my
overall decision-making process and
strategy
and I want to keep my risk low with a
higher probability of profit,
but also be realistic here. So, I could
do for example instead
perhaps a 210 long
230 short,
right? Which is a which is a call
spread, right? We discussed in the first
scenario. But now I'm going to take one
step further and I'm going to turn it
into a butterfly spread. So, now I'm
adding a third leg of the contract. I'm
selling two of the middle strike here.
So, I'm buying one 210, selling two
230s, and buying one 250. Now notice my
debit here is $4 and change. My maximum
upside is from the first leg to the
middle strike, which is $20 wide.
Um and so I have upside here about $16
based on risk of um of $4 and change.
And you actually have two different
break-even um strikes here because
essentially if we overshoot the middle
strike here and go to like let's say for
example like 240,
you would still win,
right? You would only lose if we uh
maximum loss if we overshot past 250.
But as we pass through the the body,
which is the middle strike, that's um
each each side of this is called a wing,
right? So the lowest strike is a wing
and the and the highest strike is a
wing. The middle strike is the body,
right? As we move toward the body,
the profit uh the P&L will actually
improve in your favor, right? And as
time decay kicks away and we move toward
the expiration day, it'll improve more
and more and more. So you wouldn't
target a maximum profit on this
position. You wouldn't target like a max
gain um because then you'd be pretty
much saying, "I think that Nvidia will
expire at 230 on the nose at 4:00 p.m.
on July 17th and hold that price into
after hours, in which case I would make
maximum profit." It's just not a
realistic
um expectation overall.
So
what you want to do is is is you want to
perhaps think about it in a more
realistic framework and say, "You know
what? If and when this doubles in value
and goes from, you know, $4 to $8 or $9
or $10, at that point in time, I will
then sell the position and reposition
myself based upon what I'm seeing at
that point in time."
Because ultimately if if nothing happens
here and and Nvidia just kind of ticks
away
and uh time decay kicks in, you're going
to see this position gradually increase
in profit because what will happen is
the middle strike here will lose most of
its value. This contract here has not
much value to lose already. And then
your highest strike highest delta the
here will lose some value due to the
time decay, but because it's with within
the realistic range of of the
the implied move,
you'll still have a fair amount of value
there.
So, um I won't get into into adjusting
position because again, like the
conversation can get very long here.
Like I can talk for like, you know, 50
hours on on different topics around
this, right? And when when I work with
people one-on-one, typically we spend 25
hours one-on-one going over all these
topics,
um which is why these sessions have to
be shorter, obviously, right? So again,
the opposite scenario, let's say you're
bearish, you would just switch this to a
put position, and perhaps you would say,
"Okay, I'm going to buy a let's let's
look at, you know, an out-of-the-money
position instead of at the money,
right?"
So, 200 strike long, let's go to for
example the the 185 strike short, and
we'll go to the 170 on the long over
here. This is a $50 wide butterfly put
spread,
and now you see we have an outlay of $2
roughly
for upside of $15 because the maximum
profit here is from the middle strike to
the long strike here, uh the highest
strike. So, $15 minus two is 13. You
have upside of 13 on two risk, right?
That's your maximum loss.
Uh and again, if you go back to the to
the to the to the rule I mentioned of
cutting your position at half of maximum
loss, let's say it runs runs like 230
for example, and it goes to a dollar,
you lose a dollar. You cannot have any
risk, I mean, sorry, any reward without
risk. And another one of my favorite
quotes is in life, the biggest risk
isn't taking no risk at all. Think about
that for a sec.
Um
So, beyond this,
looking at butterfly spreads, there
there are more more permutations of of
strategies you can use, you know, call
condors or put condors. Again, if you
want to Google those strategies, you
can. I won't delve deeply in each
strategy because the point of the
conversation here is how to grow a small
account, not how to focus on any
strategy um individually. If you have
any questions about this,
you know, DM me on Discord, drop a
comment on the YouTube channel. Like one
of those things is totally fine. And
I'll reply when I can.
Um let's move forward to the next
conversation point.
Um 1 second.
So the next strategy here is called a
poor man's covered call. This is a more
patience uh
or sorry
patient patients required strategy
overall because you're pretty much just
collecting premium.
And essentially what you're doing here
is
instead of owning the underlying asset,
if you own 100 shares of Nvidia for
example,
you have the ability to sell one call
option against your position um whenever
you want essentially. And you can
harvest premium
by doing that.
So if you have a smaller account, you
can't obviously buy 100 shares at you
know,
20 21 grand roughly for 100 shares.
So instead of that, you might say okay,
well you know what? I'm going to buy
perhaps a
longer dated option.
I'm going to buy perhaps let's go to
like
August or September perhaps, right? They
go to September here.
I can buy for instance right now if I go
in the money. Again, more risk obviously
because you're you're spending more
premium. But let's say you buy the 180
strike here for like $36 roughly, right?
The break even there is 180 plus 36,
which is 216.
I can buy this for September OPEX, 94
days away.
Keep in mind my break even is is 216.
So I can sell call options on shorter
shorter durations
um above my strike price
to harvest premium and reduce my cost
basis. Let's say for example, I go to
to July 17th again, right? The same
expiration date.
And let's say that I want to sell
the 220 strike price call option against
my
in-the-money call option.
I can do that.
I would be harvesting premium here of
about $4.50 roughly
on my 36
36 risk overall. So, on that risk there,
if for example, we sit below 220, the
short strike over here,
what would happen? I'm making
I'm making essentially
$4.50
on 36 risk.
I'm making 12 and 1/2% return on my risk
harvesting that position. Now, if it
pushes above 220 by July 17th,
I may be forced to close the position
out entirely, but in that case, I would
I would gain an additional profit of 220
to
216, which which is my break even, minus
$4.50 from the credit received on this
short call option here.
So, I would have a profit there of an
additional roughly $10 or so.
So, my my return there would be about 10
on 30 on 36 roughly. Oh, sorry. It'd be
10 on 32 because you're you're reducing
your risk by from 36 down to
32 by selling that July OpEx contract.
So, you'd be returning 31.25%
percentage return in, you know, 31 days.
Pretty remarkable percentage return, but
again, not without risk because you're
holding this long contract here,
which comprises pretty much 32% of of
your portfolio, or so. And if Nvidia
sells off heavily, you could see a
decent-sized loss. Although, you're
you're buying a lot of time on your
contract, so you're not too concerned
about it dropping too too much in the
short term because you have a lot of
time on the contract. But again, this is
an example of a poor man's covered call
where you're harvesting premium
recurringly on a longer-dated uh call
option. Let's say after, for example,
after July op ex,
we say just below 220,
and your call for
September is around like $38 or $40 per
contract, well, then what do you do
then, right? You look at perhaps the
following month,
the August op ex,
and then you sell perhaps the
230 call option or the 220 call option
again, right? And each time you do that,
you got to keep track of your math,
obviously, and you subtract the cost um
uh or say the debit cost of the contract
from your net cost of your longer-term
contract. So, let's say you initially
bought this September contract for 36,
and then you sold the July one for $4
and change. Now, your cost basis goes
from 36 down to 32, roughly, right?
Then, assuming everything expire uh
everything expires worthless, you're
still holding your September op ex
contract.
Then, you sell this contract at the 230
strike for like $6, for example, right?
Now, your cost basis goes from 32 down
to 26. So, you can recurringly lower
your cost basis there.
The only thing is, it's just a slow
grind, right? Because you you're you're
capturing premium every 30 days or so,
right? Um
it's a good strategy for smaller
accounts, but it's a patience-based
strategy where you got to kind of sit
and wait. Um not a terrible option,
especially if you're looking at, you
know, a cheaper stock that has high IV.
A good way to look at
um
look for opportunities is is to scan for
high implied volatility rank or
percentile using a scanner. Again, I
won't delve into that topic right now
because we're time constrained as it
stands right now.
So, beyond that, if you were to go from
a, you know, a poor man's covered call
into a discussion on
what happens as your portfolio grows a
little bit more perhaps, right?
Well, beyond that there's a strategy
which is very interesting and there are
some funds that actually employ this
strategy
um pretty often. But there is a
um
a strike called cash secured puts
obviously, right? So, cash secured puts
are where essentially you have the cash
in your portfolio to buy a given asset
times 100 shares.
And instead of buying that asset, you
say, "You know what? I'm going to sell
put option if we get below that strike
price by the expiration date, I will be
forced to take ownership of that
position assuming I don't close it out
prematurely."
So,
let's say for example that we look at
again
uh Nvidia just to be consistent here.
Um although you
you might find much much better
opportunities than using Nvidia for this
example, right? But let's say that you
go to again maybe like the August OpEx
and you say, "I'm cool with selling for
example the 180 strike put option for $3
um as a cash secured put position." Not
a lot of credit received, right? Like
you're you're pulling in $3 of credit.
Your risk is 180 essentially minus three
which is 177. Although I would argue
that the probability of Nvidia going
down to zero in the next 66 days is not
very high. Um nonetheless, it's a very
very slow way to grow your account. Not
a wrong way to do it, just a very slow
way to do it, right? Because even if you
have a margin account with like 10K in
it for example, you would be allowed to
sell a cash secured put here um because
your brokerage would say, "Okay, well,
in a worst case scenario that person
will then own 100 shares of Nvidia which
will be used as collateral for their
position overall." So, you can do it if
you wanted to, but is it the optimal
strategy? I would argue using
butterflies or verticals are far more
um conducive to growing your portfolio
in a more timely manner than
cash secured puts. Cash secured puts are
great if you have a larger portfolio
where you have tons of capital and
you're trying to cash flow your your
your cash essentially, right? Like you
know, I have I have I have 5 million
bucks in my portfolio. I'm going to go
ahead and sell
whatever like 50 contracts at the 180
strike price
for August. I'll capture, you know, $3
per contract, right? And that is
meaningful premium. That's about $15,000
of credit in your account, you know,
over the course of
you know, 2 months roughly, right?
So, you're cash flowing your your larger
portfolio.
Um there is a strategy which you can go
beyond as well, which once you once you
get to about 20 30k portfolio size,
there are certain funds that will
actually sell the strategy under like a
kind of like a mutual fund or like an
ETF vehicle.
And it's called a short covered
strangle. Essentially, you would buy
the asset, for example, in video in this
case, you buy
let's say 100 shares.
And then what you would do is you would
sell a call option against your stock
and at the same time sell a cash secured
put. Essentially, selling
the the strangle, the call out of the
money and the put out of the money and
capturing that, which would reduce your
cost basis overall. So, an example of
that would be, for example, you buy 100
shares at let's say 208 right now.
Looking at the July OPEX again.
Let's go back to here.
You would sell, for example, the
220 strike price for 450
on the call side. You sell that.
And then on the put side, you would sell
perhaps the 200 strike put option for
470.
Credit received here is
not 17. It's It's like $10 roughly or $9
roughly. So, you're putting in $9 credit
overall and essentially if Nvidia stays
between 200 and 220,
your cost basis drops from 208 down to
like 199 on your shares that you own.
And if it goes to 220
for example, it's the upside,
you would then make $11 of profit on
your position in addition to the $9 you
have right here. So, you make about $20
overall of profit on 208 which is about
like 9% return in the span of a month.
Not bad at all whatsoever. Again, this
strategy is better for larger portfolios
because you can as you get larger, you
don't care so much about the dollar
denominated I'm sorry, the percentage
gains. Those gains can be smaller while
the dollars are larger, right? If your
cost of living is pretty fixed and your
portfolio is growing, you're not really
concerned about, you know, making higher
percentage percentage returns perhaps,
but the dollar returns are meaningful
because as they balloon,
assuming you do not you do not
increase your standard of of living
dramatically.
By that I mean I'm like making more
money and going by you know, buying a
new car, getting a larger house, buying,
you know, a new Rolex for example,
whatever. Like the point is is that
if all else remaining equal, as your
portfolio grows, this position
uh sorry, [clears throat] this strategy
will give you a very, very nice return
overall because you can cash flow
your larger portfolio and it's
meaningful enough that you actually
enjoy the benefits of it. Whereas in a
smaller portfolio, you know, making $800
or or 900 bucks in the course of like,
you know, a month out for example, it
might not be very conducive to a good a
good living for most people unless you
have a job or some other form of income
that is helping you to live overall.
Um
now beyond that,
the last thing I want to mention
before we take some Q&A
was
liquidity, right? So,
we focus on all these different
strategies, but
the important thing is
you want to use these strategies only on
liquid options where where you have very
tight bid-ask spreads, like, you know,
SPY, triple Qs, Nvidia,
Tesla, for example, whatever. Any names
that have high volume trading on the
underlying asset. So, like, if you look
at if you look at an option chain on a
given day, and by the way, the easiest
way to correlate this is looking at the
average daily volume a stock trades on a
given day
correlates heavily with the amount of
volume each day on the option chain.
So, for example, if you look at Nvidia
today, it's already traded 1.13 million
contracts in one single day.
Today, I think I think SpaceX has traded
like
I don't know, a crazy amount of
contracts.
Uh where where where we at now, right?
1 million as well, right?
Um you know, on Microsoft, for example,
right? Um you you like you can go you
can go on uh uh
uh on and on about this, but like
the the point being is that if you're
using strategies where the spreads are
very wide,
you're going to have a lot of slippage,
meaning meaning that if you want to buy
a position, you need to go
um closer to the actual ask price,
meaning that you're paying a higher
premium overall. And then when you want
to sell it, you need to go closer to the
to the to the to the to the bid price.
So, that gap right there is called is
called the spread, and the wider the
spread, the more the slippage you and
you're um you're going to incur overall,
right? Kind of why also people don't
really trade heavily NDX options on
Nasdaq because the volume isn't as high
there as, for example, SPX, right? So,
you want to have
typically very, very tight spreads.
If you notice that the spread between
the bid and the ask is in excess of 10%
of the of the overall cost, you want to
stay away from it, right? So, let's say,
for example, it was like like $5 um uh
cost for a contract, and the spread is
like 50 cents or more, you want to stay
away from it. Typically, you want to be
you want to be in for like a 10 cent
spread, 20 cent spread, not really more
than that because otherwise slippage
would eat you alive and would eat into
your profits and it you pretty much
every trade you start off at
a loss because you paid more than you
should have for the contract and when
you sell it, you're going to lose a bit
of money on that as well. So, keep that
in mind. That's also why if you guys
notice, you know, what I talk about
predominantly mega cap names because I'm
always trading pretty much highly liquid
names that have no slippage essentially,
right? Or low slippage.
So, beyond that, I think we're finished
in this conversation for
volatility. We're about 45 minutes in
roughly, guys.
Um let me just make sure I covered
everything here.
Yeah.
Yeah, so yeah, avoid options where
there's no
no liquidity at all. If you find some
like random biotech stock or
like whatever the the name is, if it has
no volume in the option chain and the
spreads are wide, just avoid it. They
will eat your lunch. The spreads will
eat your lunch, okay?
And the last thing is
um strike and expiration selection. So,
there's zero day versus weekly versus
monthly. They're different trade-offs,
right? Zero day trading,
whatever you put in, be ready to say
goodbye to it because that money could
be gone that day. But, also can have
crazy asymmetry of risk because you're
paying a much much lower premium for a
given contract, right? If you go to
Nvidia and look at, you know, contracts
expired tomorrow versus, you know, a
week out versus a month out,
let's say we get a move on Nvidia.
Let me a second. Let me go back to the
option chain again.
And we'll do Q&A right after this, guys,
too.
So, let's say for example, on Nvidia,
you go to
tomorrow's op-ex. Oh, sorry, this is
triple Q, right? So,
actually, this is fine too, right? So,
you can trade zero days on on the Qs
today, right? It's it's currently at
p.m. Eastern time right now, and we're
at
7:35 roughly.
Let's say buy this contract, 7:33 buy
straight call option. This expires in
like 3 hours time basically, right? So,
you might buy this contract for you
know, for $130 roughly.
But, unless you push above 3
7:35 by at least 1:30, you're probably
going to lose money on that position.
Although, if we get for example some
crazy headline like
I don't know.
Um
It could be anything whatever. I mean,
we've seen the craziest headlines the
last few weeks around the the Iran war
where they're like, "Yeah, we have a
deal. No, we're attacking. No, we have a
deal. No, we're attacking, right?" And
what happens? The price action on
zero-day contracts is absolutely insane.
Like, I remember
I think it was last week
on Tuesday like
one week ago today, where we had that V
bottom on SPX.
And there were out-of-the-money
contracts that went from like $2 each to
like $5 a piece sorry, $50 a piece.
So, you turn pretty much like $200 $200
into $5,000 in the same day. But again,
looking at it at that point in time,
you're like, "Okay, well, the
probability of us recovering 100 points
in the last 4 hours of trading isn't
very high, right?" So, I would say that
growing a small account is all about
patience and discipline.
Chasing those fast returns will
typically erase that aspiration by
depleting your account such that you see
it get cut in half, and then you get
more laissez faire with with your uh or
more cavalier with how you're handling
your funds, and then before you know it,
you pretty much burn 10K in capital. And
I'm sure many of many of you guys have
done this before in the past. I mean, I
know many people that have blown up
accounts.
The point is
think about this as as a practice round
for when you have more capital by saving
your money from your job or whatever it
is that you you do to make money. And as
you're practicing and learning your
process and honing your process,
you can see the the
in real time.
Right? If you can make, you know, 5K a
off 10K over the course of 6 or 7
months, which doesn't sound very sexy to
most people, but I think it's a very
very good learning experience.
You're probably going to be be able to
make, for example, 50K off 100K, right?
And as you scale more and more, the same
things apply, but the problem is
those fast gains that people chase where
they take binary outcomes like, you
know, for example, zero-day contracts
where they buy a whole bunch of them
hoping for a massive home run.
It's not a repeatable process. You might
get lucky one time, but if you do that
every time, over over time you're going
to be at zero pretty much.
So, I will end the discussion there and
open up for Q&A.
Any questions here, guys?
Let's see what we we have in chat here.
Okay, so
uh
Yeah, someone said
we should rename the series from how to
how to build your small account to how
to stop making your small account
smaller. Uh that's a good point. Um
Yep, that's with Fidelity.
Chris asked, "Nick, if you do the fly on
any American sell option, you just want
to make sure you close it out before
expiration, correct?" Yes, very very
good question there, Chris.
Um if you're opening a butterfly
position and you're holding it toward
expiration, you want to be
sure you close it out because if you
don't close it out, what will happen is
that assuming you have the capital in
your account to actually take ownership
of your position,
you will then be assigned
let's say, for example, that on on
Nvidia again, right? Let's say that you
bought that 210 230
uh 250 call call fly, and we expire at
like 215, for example, right? And you
forget about it. What will happen is
that if you have the capital in your
account,
your brokerage will say, "Okay, cool.
Nick wanted to own this position. He
didn't close it out. Therefore, the call
will be assigned, right?" Well, what
will happen there is if I'm on the call
option, I'm going to call away 100
shares from someone else's account
or from my counterparty.
Therefore, I'll be long 100 shares at
in my account on the following Monday
after expiration.
So, very, very important to think. If
we're above the middle strike, that's
where it gets kind of funky because if
you have the capital in your account to
take assignment of of the whole
position,
what would happen then is that if you
for example on a call fly, let's say you
had you know 210,
230,
250 again,
right here.
Right? And and you're short here.
Remember, you're short two contracts at
the middle strike.
Let's say this happened right here,
right? Well, if we expire at for example
like 232 and you forgot about it, what
would happen is you'd be assigned
the call option at 210 and two of the
call options at 230.
So,
in essence, the one one of the calls
would be washed away because you're long
210, but you're short 230. One of them
would be washed away, but the second
contract would be assigned to you me and
because you're short a call option, that
means that you would have you you'd have
shares called away from your account
even if you don't own them.
So, what would happen is on the
following Monday following expiration,
you'd be short 100 shares in your
account of Nvidia at 230 per share.
So, if they had you know news on Monday
morning where they were like announcing
some new product or something like that
and went like 250, you'd see a massive
fat loss.
So,
always blow out your positions out
before expiration or if you're using
IBKR, there is a there is a an actual
option to lapse your contracts, right?
You can say lapse your contract, but
that only applies to long contracts, not
short contracts. In this case, you're
long 210, you're short 230. If you're
above 230, you have no right to say
lapse. If you let it expire assuming you
have the margin in your account
available to actually take assignment,
you will let me assigned on the Monday
following expiration.
So, good observation there, Chris. And
good question as well.
Um
John asked, uh "Operationally, what goes
into your consideration when choosing
July or August OPEX or far out
expiration in general? I know I I know I
know the literal definition of, let's
say, higher IV for the route. What's on
your mind?"
So, I mean, when I I look at um
uh expiration date selection, I'm
looking at perhaps uh is there a binary
event following that expiration date
where I'm paying a premium for that? An
earning event, for example, right? Um is
there some kind of, you know, like macro
event like FOMC, which is tomorrow, for
example, right? Is there a uh an
election in November, for example,
right? If you're buying longer dated
options, they don't really price in
those events cuz you're paying much,
much, more
um nominal prices on on a daily basis. A
good A good practice to kind of use, if
you want, as as a as a kind of like a
exercise,
look at different contracts across
different strikes and divide the cost of
that contract by the days to expiration.
You'll notice that
the more time you buy, the less you're
paying on a daily contract, right?
Um
being like
A uh decent metaphor for this would be
kind of like buying auto insurance,
right? Let's say, for example, you could
buy auto insurance where you're paying
like 500 bucks um a month for your auto
insurance, and if and when you need that
auto insurance on a given month, you
then use it and it's useful to you.
But, if you buy it, for example, like a
year out, maybe you're paying instead of
paying six grand a year, you're paying
like three grand for the year, right? A
much, much cheaper cost overall. The
reason being is that
you have it there in the event that you
need it over the next 1-year period. In
the same vein that anything can happen
when you buy a call option that expires
in a year, for for example, right? The
time decay is very low. Typically, the
IV is low because no one else in the
market is really focusing on those
contracts. Most participants in the
market are focusing on short duration
contracts
uh because they are they have the best
asymmetry of risk or if you're an option
seller, you're like, you know what? I
want to capture premium. I don't think
anybody's going to go to go to 215 by
Friday. I'll sell the Friday or the
Friday contract assuming that the Friday
contract um this Friday is a holiday, by
the way, so. Um
Yeah, you you you you want to look at IV
skew, um John, and you want to look at
obviously uh binary events, right? Are
there are there competitors are uh
reporting earnings before me? Is this an
industry event? Is there, you know, is
there a macro event, for example, right?
A lot of things going going to your
overall thought process as well as what
is my overall thesis here? Um am I am I
long-term bullish? Am I short-term
bullish? Am I medium-term bullish,
right? Am I short-term bearish,
medium-term bearish, long-term bearish,
right? Many, many things are going to
enter the thought process there. Again,
when I teach people one-on-one, which I
do um
uh like I've been doing for the past 11
years, roughly,
um
we talk we talk about all these
different topics over 25 hours, roughly.
So, cramming all that into like an hour
discussion is impossible, pretty much.
Um
Mike asked question on a $10,000
account, you can't buy 100 100 shares of
Nvidia, so this this or the per month
covered call example, both use a large
amount of the account or all of it in
one shot. Yes, that's correct, yeah. So,
um if you have 10 10 grand in your
account in a margin account, your margin
will allow you to buy 100 shares of
Nvidia, probably. I don't know what your
broker is.
Um but that means that you're using
pretty much your entire account in one
position. Yes, that's correct, right?
So, if you do the per month covered
call, you'd be using you know, in the
money call options. You can also buy
shorter duration if you wanted to and
cuz Nvidia has, for example, Monday,
Wednesday, Friday expiration, you could
be cute with it and try and sell, you
know, Monday out of the money options or
calls, then Wednesday out of the money
calls, and then Friday out of the money
calls, recurringly pulling in more
premium, but again, I think less is
more, especially with smaller accounts.
You're better off taking mid mid to
longer term positioning and you and and
then um
like having a thesis where you have good
asymmetry of risk, let it play out over
time, and this way if you're incorrect,
you're not going to burn too fast. On
zero-day contracts or similar
expiration, you see pretty much a binary
outcome, either big profit or a big
gain, right? I mean, sorry, a big profit
or a big loss.
Um
Hope that helps, Mike.
>> [clears throat]
>> Um
okay.
John posted, "I saw release four out of
the out of the money zero DTE you call
when we went 75 75, it made sense. For
expiration feels hard to discern." Yeah,
more of a comment there, I guess.
John asks,
um "Nick, what are your thoughts on
selling a put around support a year out
and buying shares at half the premium to
close at 50%?"
So, I love that strategy. That's That's
a strategy for for larger accounts,
right? Like when I talk about it in the
morning meetings,
um
especially during times of higher
volatility when the money is lower
typically and and VIX is higher,
you want to be selling out of the money
put options to finance uh call spreads
perhaps on names you want to own. Like
right now, Microsoft is at, you know, um
390-ish. Selling a 350 put option below
the the current lows of the year to
finance like a 400 500 call spread is
not a terrible idea overall, right? But
you want that higher higher um IV across
the board
to sell a premium. Again, when you go
out that far in duration, um
typically the the skew favors uh lower
prices for
uh for longer-dated options, right?
You're paying mostly for time for time
premium. There is some value baked in
there as well, obviously, too.
Um
I think Willie asked, "I'm assuming a
short collar position will require both
the shares and the potential cash to
cover the put being assigned."
Yeah, uh if yeah, if you're shorting a
collar, so
I guess you you mean to sell a call
option to finance a some option.
Uh I mean that that would be a that
would be a a long collar, right?
Um a short collar
I'm not sure what what a short collar
is. Do you mean selling a put option to
buy a call option?
I'm I'm I'm going to assume you mean
just a collar, right? So, a collar is
where you own 100 shares, for example,
and let's say you want you want 100 100
shares of immediate right here. What you
could do, and this is kind of a cool
strategy, too, is you can use something
called a a calendar collar. I'll explain
a collar first, but basically, let's say
that you bought 100 shares right now.
You said, "You know what? I'm going to
cap my gains, but I'm going to I'm going
to cap my losses as well over the next
30 days. So, I'm going to sell, for
example, the 230 call option against my
100 shares,
and I'm going to use that premium, 235
roughly premium, to finance the I'll say
the 190 strike put options.
So, I'm capping my gains
at 230, but I'm also capping my losses
at 190 as well, right? Great strategy to
use through binary events like again
like midterm elections, um elections,
FOMCs,
any kind of binary event, collars are
great assuming you do not mind losing
your shares at the call strike price
because you might lose your calls, for
example, right? I mean, your shares, for
example, right? Um there is a better
strategy which I like as well,
especially when IV is very high,
is to look at selling calendar collars
where I mean calendars um
uh
uh collars where, for example, you would
sell it let's say the January position.
Let's say you bought 100 shares of of
immediate right right here today,
and you're concerned about perhaps next
earning event or something like that,
right? Well, you can go out of the
money, sell the 250 call options for $50
apiece,
take that premium and use it to finance
insurance through binary events on
shorter duration. Let's say, for
example, you want to hedge yourself
through August, right?
So, you go to August like you know what?
I'll buy the $200 put option here for $8
and change. And because you pulled in
premium on the January contract, you're
now hedged into August,
not beyond that.
You're capping your gains into August as
well, but you have a credit here of $6
roughly.
So, let's say we pushed like 250 by
August,
you might be like, yeah, you know what?
I was cool with capping my gains not a
big deal, whatever. But also, I'm not
concerned about losing money in the
short term if there's some kind of new
minor event or exogenous risk event or
whatever happens in the next couple
months.
Um hopefully that helps there. We're
approaching an hour, guys, so I'm
planning to cut it off after Let me see.
Um
Last question here, okay?
Uh John asked, different John. There's
like
three or four Johns in this chat, common
name here.
Um can I ask around how many strategies
you you something something something
you're managing at a given time?
I'm trading
a lot of strategies at once, you know. I
have cash secured puts out. I have leap
leaps out on certain names that I own. I
have call spreads. I have butterfly call
spreads, butterfly put spreads perhaps
if if I'm so inclined, if I'm bearish
perhaps.
Um I'll have calendar spreads out. Um
yeah, like
basically the the way you got to think
about it is like understand each
strategy kind of like a chess player
understands what strategy to to use to
counter their opponent. Whenever I see a
certain scenario, I'm like, okay, what's
the most optimal way to to approach this
scenario given my current thesis and my
desired reward to risk ratio overall.
So,
hopefully that helps, guys. We're at an
hour right now. I'm going to cut it off
right here.
Um you guys were great. Thank you very
much for your time. Do you have any
comments at all? Drop them below in the
YouTube video below. I'll post the
recording as well for you guys.
Um and if you have any any questions at
all, hit me up in Discord as well. My
name is Braxton in the chat. So, you
guys can find me there.
Otherwise, guys, hopefully that was
great and informative. Um have a great
day and manage your risk, and we'll
we'll talk soon.